[Music]
this update to our sense-making series
which started about a month ago with
what the fuck is going on and in that
film i talked about the crisis in
journalism especially the crisis in
American journalism American media and
so much has happened even in the last
few weeks and few days but I think it's
worth doing an update and I think why
this is so significant is that it's a
crisis with an American journalism but
by extension it's a crisis within
truth-seeking within sense-making and
this has huge consequences for everyone
in the rest of the world I think one of
the things that may be one of the
unexpected consequences of the big tech
platforms kind of domination the fact
that almost all of us get most of our
media through the tech platforms is that
it's kind of globalized the American
culture war to the rest of the world so
we're all influenced by it whether or
not we want to be and just on that
there's another film coming up in the
next couple of days with Tristan Harris
who's been described as the conscience
of Silicon Valley who's made it his
mission to look at how the big tech
platforms are boosting polarization
boosting division and what we might be
able to do about it to get attention
within that debt sphere I have to use
outrage so both sides the left and the
right are using outrage to get people to
get to get people's attention and then
that just further Cleaves the kind of
divide so just in the last few days
they've been a few really major events
in American media Barry Weiss the
opinion editor at The New York Times who
wrote the original intellectual dark web
piece and has been a sort of champion of
heterodox opinion within the New York
Times has left with a really kind of
biting and quite detailed resignation
letter and also Andrew Sullivan who was
one of the few conservative columnist
sat the New York Magazine has also left
so I think the overall frame for Barry
Weiss in the New York Times just
something she talks about in a letter is
that the election of Trump in 2016
should have been a time for people on
the more liberal side to stop and think
about why people were voting for Trump
what it was about kind of the way that
liberalism was showing up
the increased kind of intolerance with
other views that was making people or
pushing people towards Trump and
actually the opposite seems to have
happened so she says in her resignation
letter the lessons that ought to have
followed the election lessons about the
importance of understanding other
Americans the necessity of resisting
tribalism the centrality of the free
exchange of ideas to a Democratic
Society have not been learned instead a
new consensus has emerged in the press
but perhaps especially at this paper the
truth isn't a process of collective
discovery but an orthodoxy already known
to an enlightened few whose job is to
inform everyone else but the main thing
I wanted to talk about was the Harper's
letter there was a letter that was
originally conceived of by Thomas
Chatterton Williams who we had on
recently on this channel and it brought
together the attempt was to draw a line
in the sand so three paragraphs of
fairly mild defenses of free speech and
calling out the attacks on free speech
on both the right and the left that was
then signed by a host of people from
academia from the literary world
including people like Salman Rushdie
Margaret Atwood Noam Chomsky Malcolm
Gladwell and JK Rowling but it caused a
huge backlash so to unpack all of this I
thought the best person to speak to
would be Jessie single who we
interviewed recently for the death of
journalism piece so Jessie's a freelance
journalist who's written for a lot of
these institutions and also has recently
set up the blocks and reported podcast
with Katy Hertzog so it kind of gives
him a frontside view of everything
that's going on but also gives him a
certain sense of freedom and detachment
from it now that allow them to really
speak his mind we recorded only like
three weeks ago with a piece that I put
out called the death of journalism which
I thought might be a little bit kind of
click Beatty but it doesn't appear to be
and like this kind of dumpster fire or I
think what you called an epistemic break
in journalism sort of has continued to
ramp up over the last kind of couple of
weeks since we spoke last I'd like to
start by by that frame like you said an
epistemic break and that
felt really right to me like there's
something in the norms and the way that
things have happened over the last few
weeks that seems to suggest that
something's really shifted so maybe
we'll talk about that first and then
talk about what some of the actual
events are for people who maybe aren't
on twitter as much as we are and and i
think i did this last time but i'd like
to first apologize for my Haggard jewish
caveman look this is a an experiment
during the pandemic I'm usually a little
bit more put together than this but um
yeah I mean it's important to talk about
this stuff in a clear way
I think journalism still the majority or
the vast majority of people in
journalism writing journalism because
they're interested in the truth and
they're not just in it out of politics
they they might have politics like mine
that are broadly progressive and they
don't hide that but that's that's
different from seeing Paul journalism
specifically as like a tool for
advancing very narrow political claims
and what we're basically seeing is like
less and less of a sense that journalism
is separate from activism journalism is
just sort of employed as a tool for
activism and as I wrote about in my in
my newsletter
they've just been sort of a series of
alarm bells in recent years about this
one of them was was the big covington
case where a short video seemed to
indicate that a group of mostly white
kids from the catholic school were
harassing a Native American activist I
watched as professional journalists even
when a longer video was revealed that
that really made it seem much more
complicated in that and much more like
the activists sort of walked into the
circle of kids who are already chanting
and cheering then that they had harassed
him anyway the worst thing you could say
about some of these kids was that they
did the tomahawk chop which is
considered offensive by some Native
Americans but it's also something tens
of thousands of American sports fans do
every day if any of your viewers are
confused by that you can just google it
and get an explanation so I what in
online and offline discussions I watched
journalists refused to see what was
before their own eyes like the video
certain aspects of this were made very
clear by the video but it seemed like
this sort of incentives to come out
against the Covington kids because
we need it either before or against
everything and there can never be any
complexity worse we're so overwhelming
that people just sort of let their own
values and social incentives override
what was on a video in front of it and
it was very much people of course
overuse or well in these situations but
that whole like how many blinking lights
are in front of you not being able to
say what the answer is disturb the hell
out of me and Covington was not the most
important story by a longshot but but it
just pointed to these trajectories in
journalism that just worried the hell
out of me and and that are bad so that's
the long winded under caffeinated answer
yeah it's like that
it's the Asch conformity experiment
isn't it where you have the sort of
three people give a wrong answer and all
of them are in on it and it's the one
person who goes along or doesn't go
along even though what they're seeing in
front of their eyes is is not and is not
true well not only that but I mean the
the Asch conformity experiment which i
think some of the results have been
overplayed over the years because a lot
of people did not go with the crowd I
forget the exact number either way
there's a guy Dan kahan at yeah well I
always reference just a brilliant he's
trained as a legal scholar I think but
there's a lot of psychology and he has
this idea that our views on these issues
are really determined by our social
networks and and our religious and
political networks and the Asch
conformity experiment showed that even
in a situation where there's no moral or
political valence where the only thing
at stake was you know going against a
group of strangers a fair number of
people would give an objectively wrong
answer to not go against the crowd you
add to that the sense that you're doing
something morally or politically wrong
or that you're sort of going against the
group or betraying the group and and
people just go crazy and then you add
the social media landscape which is
brutal where you get instant feedback
with every opinion you express and it's
just it's adding up to something really
ugly that this is not the cause of
journalism's problems the cause of
journalism problems are wide-ranging and
structural and journalism is totally
screwed
but journalism is in the process of
furthering its own screwing or
accelerating it by
by just adopting these really bad
standards that the average person
understands and can see what's going on
and that it's increasingly not about
truth or journalism
as so so let's just recap sort of some
of the things that have happened
recently there was the the Harper's
letter which was quite a kind of Anna
dying fairly vanilla letter which was
three paragraphs of sort of talking
about the value of free expression and
may pains to criticize both sides it
talked about the right as well as the
left but talked about a censorious
nasaan the left that was signed by a
huge number of kind of the great and
good of writers and any poker one sir
and some mediocre ones to the great ones
like yourself and Katie and then some
people no one's ever heard of like sarin
rush to hassle you know Salman Rushdie
those many people but then it just
caused this incredible shit show online
even while the left it was was fairly
kind of mild and what it was what it was
kind of trying to assert mainstream
outlets immediately just misrepresented
the letter and basically crept right up
to the line of lying about this because
that's if you're responding to a letter
by saying this person saying acts when
they didn't say X that's pretty close to
a lie or a bad faith reading and tried
to impugn the motives of the people in
the letter who signed the letter without
pointing to any evidence they believed
what you claim they believe there's all
these sort of bad faith and and since
aureus maneuvers that's the sort of
environment we're in right now and it's
not fun and I think what pissed me off
the most of all it was people saying
there was a counter letter that said
that look at these powerful people who
signed a letter they're afraid they're
gonna get cancelled
no I'm I'm at this point not afraid I'm
getting it cancelled of course I'm
worried crazy people will occupy
gatekeeping roles in journalism and make
it harder for me to write for The Times
or whatever but at the moment one of the
reasons I felt safe signing the letter
is I'm I'm not easily canceled at the
moment like I have independent income I
have a book deal I'm very fortunate and
I want it to be the case that other
people can be as free as I am to express
my opinions without fear of some asshole
trying to get me fired and that annoyed
the hell out because like nobody
actually thinks steven pinker is afraid
he's getting out to get fired or noam
chomsky it's just it's so remarkably bad
faith to say oh yeah oh no Chomsky's is
afraid he's gonna get fired and i just
you know as i say this out loud there
are journalists working in war zones
they're journalists trying to review
what the Chinese government is doing to
an ethnic minority which might be
tantamount to genocide and and I don't
think it's a good look for us New York
and Brooklyn media types - just the
amount of energy spent on these bullshit
claims of harassment that are not you
know I feel bad for Barry I feel bad for
the Vox Stafford journalists go through
some serious shit that is not people on
Twitter yelling at you or even making
death threats at you like Twitter's
crazy I just the amount of focus spent
on these sort of intro left journalism
issues it does not benefit us in the
long run even if in the moment they feel
import and they are important in a way
it's just like the the sheer amount of
energy and time we spend on this stuff
is not good and I'm including myself in
this yeah I agree I think going into the
kind of minutiae I of it is very inside
baseball and seems very sort of
self-indulgent which is why I thought
that the main piece was the epistemic
break like what does it mean if you're
an organization that is supposedly
aligned around truth but actually you're
seeing an increasing lack of truth in
sort of what's being reported that's why
I think the epistemic break piece is
such a vital point to come back to when
you're actually talking about situation
and people are misrepresenting or
ignoring the facts of that situation
like that seems to be a really
fundamental problem yeah yeah I agree I
mean that that isn't inside baseball
that's the question of how big outlets
do their job and like you know one of my
newsletters is about the epistemic break
I mentioned Cummington another was you
know Vox purporting to investigate and
explain what happened at the Times in a
way where it wasn't journalism it was
activism it was like anti Barry activism
like this guy did not try to reach out
to anyone on the other side of this
conflict within the times and I know
there are multiple people on the other
side of it even I not particularly
well-connected it's just these norms
about how journalism is conducted matter
a lot and I want to keep that separate
from the sort of online drama shit show
that's raging 24/7 but um yeah so the
epistemic breach and and the sort of
collapse of journalistic norms in some
corners of progressive journalism it's a
big deal it affects what stories you see
and how they're covered and how major
issues are approached so as I said the
hafiz left was initially conceived by
Thomas Schatz
Williams who was recently on rebel
wisdom talking about unlearning race in
2020 but the idea that we can't talk
about certain things we're not from that
background his part seems to be part of
the problem
well absolutely that's how you you
preclude the possibility of dialogue
that's what the idea that there's what
Glenn Lowry calls and what I'm very
convinced is a real problem in today's
discourse is this idea of identity
epistemology that because I am black I
have access to some kind of knowledge
that you can never possess so the only
thing that you can do is you can be
quiet and listen and be an ally but the
only way that you can the only authentic
ally ship is silence that's not you we
all know that that can't possibly hold
that can't work that's that's that's not
how you build a multi-ethnic society
that works and you know there's a
backlash there like we talked in the
beginning of unforeseen consequences to
short-term power grabs this is partially
I don't want to say it's the only reason
but this is partially how we did end up
with someone like Trump resonating so
wildly we're creating a society where
everybody has an identity that gives
them knowledge and immorality we're
moving towards identity morality I don't
need X so everybody can be proud of
their identity and it gives them some
special insight into the human condition
except for one group and that one group
is the the group that's historically
been in power and that is aware that
it's demographically shrinking so what
does that set up that sets up a
situation where that group is going to
some of members of that group we're
going to fight like hell to to react in
the worst possible ways to this new
world that clearly signals the man who
places them so in the last piece I used
a few frames from Brett and Eric
Weinstein talking about the collapse of
sense making the collapse of the
institutions in this I want to refer
back to the blue church which Jordan
Hall talks about as the system that kind
of arose after the Second World War and
was really based on a kind of broadcast
modality and how that was increasingly
challenged
by decentralized media the blue church
emerged in the context of having to
figure out how to navigate all of these
changes in generate coherence how do we
get all of these people with these new
capacities to be able to make sense of
the world in some fashion that is able
to then make choices together and to act
effectively right that's the question
and the blue church developed to be the
answer that question answer developed
the ability to say for example use the
education system to establish an
embodied sense of vertical meritocratic
hierarchy the idea that some people are
better at others in knowing certain
kinds of things we can find them and
then we empower them to have
hierarchical authority in the structure
that we're in there is a relationship
between authority and receptor that has
a broadcast modality so the blue church
is very broadcast across its entire mode
so what I mean by a broadcast of course
is exemplified in television which is to
say that some small number of people get
to speak and a very very large number of
people get to listen and is very
different and then say but we're doing
right here and this is symmetric well of
course I'm the one speaking in principle
there's nothing about this conversation
that couldn't be perfectly symmetric but
in television and any kind of broadcast
modality it's structurally that way so
Walter Cronkite tells the news and
everybody else watches it and there's a
lot of passivity there like my job is
not to perceive what's going on make
sense of it and then express it in the
world my job is to see the story that
I'm being told and be able to then
express that story effectively in the
society that I'm in there's very good
reasons to believe that the blue church
is done meaning that it's in the
senescence stage and senescence has a
characteristic where when you move into
the senescence stage you tend to go
downhill pretty quickly so I'm expecting
to see the blue church sort of
increasingly obvious
failing and increasingly obviously
losing the habitual or unconscious or
unspoken position of being authoritative
and being just reality more and more
people are going to be going ah that's a
thing that's not the whole thing it's a
thing and it's kind of doing something
and maybe parts of it are still good but
it's not the whole thing and it seems to
be increasingly fucked up and in the
meantime looking around going okay now
what that's the key I run our in a space
we're in that space between 1918 and
1945 or in the space between 1077 BC and
800 BC where there's a gap between a
coherent collective intelligence is a
coherent structure of being able to
respond as a whole to what's happening
and a new it not an old one a nooner and
as if fading so we're witnessing that
transition we're in the middle of it and
a lot of the phenomenon that was
experiencing over the past what 15 years
or so are of that sort starting around
2000 ish particularly accelerating you
can explain a lot of the things that
happened it seemed very inexplicable
like brexit and Trump using this model
so I think this is the most helpful
frame to understand what's going on in
journalism at the moment we have an
institution that was already
increasingly fragile because the
business model was being challenged by
decentralized media and so as the
institutions get weaker they're more
vulnerable and able to be taken over do
you think that it was sort of structural
issues in journalism that have that have
kind of got it to the point where it's
been taken over by this kind of
situation how do you frame it it sort of
feels a bit like a kind of mirror of the
of the whole pandemic to me like a week
a week host being taken over via virus
in double-quick time yeah we've talked
about this a little too but some people
there's just like two simple catchphrase
that particularly people on the right
use like go won't go broke as though
people are these journalists these
outlets are struggling because of their
political stances but I think Katie and
I both think the opposite is true is
that the structural problems with
journalism go so far beyond ideology
there's just an entire
business model has collapsed a business
model that 30 years ago was such that
you know the Baltimore Sun and the
Boston Globe could have foreign bureaus
which is unthinkable now I think as an
institution collapses the culture inside
is going to get very weird and and in
this case what you see basically is that
whatever concerns upper-middle class
graduates of elite universities is more
and more what they care about and that
is where woke miss resides so yeah I
think I think obviously they feed back
into one another because like maybe
people will stop reading certain
publications as they get less and less
trustworthy but overall I'm much more in
the camp of go broke go woke and vice
versa
yeah the structural stuff ISM is a much
bigger deal and it's long and this goes
back decades this goes back to
Craigslist and then social media I mean
the business models have totally
collapse I mean just for instance like
the Seattle Times the big sort of daily
paper here 20 years ago had 5,000
staffers today they have sold their
buildings they exist on two floors in a
tiny building it was apparently the the
publisher was offered like seven hundred
and thirty million dollars in the early
2000s from you know Gannett or some like
major corporation to buy this paper and
today there's almost worthless so that I
mean that's really the issue is that the
industry is failing and the response the
responsive that has been for everybody
sort of go kind of crazy in some ways of
but it is not I think yeah the the
structural issues really precede sort of
the other things that are happening
within and I also think this is also
part of a brother a broader trend in the
culture a lot of which has to do with
sort of backlash against Donald Trump
and a lot of fear about you know him
sort of ushering into people think that
he's going to usher and you know do a
nude age of fascism or authoritarianism
and to the into the into the nation and
so there's been this sort of Ben Smith
from the New York Times calls it
resistance journalism and I do think
there has been a trend over the past
couple years for journalists to really
sort of see themselves more or maybe
they still see themselves as journalists
but they've really turned into activists
and you know and everybody sort of wants
to be on the right side of history we're
in such a weird moment in time that
people are deeply concerned about the
country understandably and they want to
sort of do the right thing but do the
right thing in this case often means
sort of shaking off these
values of journalism motive existed for
a long time obviously Brett Weinstein
has thought about this as much as anyone
after what happened to an evergreen
college this is from a forthcoming piece
that I've got with him the connection
between what's going on in the wider
world and what took place at Evergreen
is so close that it is unmistakable for
anybody who saw the initial episode
unfold as closely as we did the reason
that this is happening is that there is
an epistemology that has existed for
many years inside of the critical theory
disciplines and it evolved into a method
and that method had got tested in the
microcosm of college environments
especially evergreen so we experienced
what it was like we discovered the
various tropes and now what we are
simply seeing is that as one should have
predicted those who went to college and
learned this perspective have now moved
into positions in society some of them
in close proximity to power and they
have now begun to exert that influence
in artists when we saying that this is
the evergreening of society what was the
outcome of Evergreen because on one side
you could kind of look at it as like you
you've sort of come out you you've
started up your own podcast you you've
actually kind of managed to land on your
feet so I think many people maybe think
that evergreen ultimately was a success
story of pushing back against the
radical there is that what happened yes
and no the important thing to realize is
that there is a mapping of what happened
at Evergreen and it it reflects various
different outcomes so there is what
happened to Evergreen there's what
happened to Heather in to me and then
there is what happened to the movement
inside and if you track these things
independently and then you map them on
to civilization you'll understand where
we're headed and why I'm so worried
about it so I did land on my feet but
one thing that is important for people
who are considering their own jeopardy
to realize is that there was not room in
the outer world for an indefinite
a large number of people to play my role
so that is to say yes a small number of
people may make it out by maneuvering
maneuvering deftly through the traps and
demonstrating that it is possible
there's a hunger to see that people can
accomplish that goal and while I wasn't
able to preserve my job or Heather's job
I was able to carve out a niche in the
outer world and I'm doing fine I should
say what Heather and I have lost is the
security that our jobs provided we have
essentially none going forward one bad
tweet and things could turn around on us
but in terms of our quality of life we
we are doing fine and did not we
suffered briefly but then have recovered
based on other things we were able to do
that the world has some need for but if
you look at the institution the
institution has been utterly crippled by
what happened the movement took over
with the aid of the president because
the president partnered with the mob the
college was reduced to a laughingstock
the plans that were deployed were
crippling to the college and the loss of
reputation that came from
obviously phony ideas becoming paramount
at the school is one from which nobody
thinks it will recover so if we now map
this on to society we have a small
number of us out here in society who are
indeed able to make a living by talking
about what's gone wrong and what to
think about it but you also have a
movement that is advancing incredibly
foolish policy proposals and you have a
power structure that is cowing to it and
what will be the result it will be just
like evergreen and increasingly it seems
that the only people who can actually
speak freely are those outside the
institutions and I wanted to come to
some we we were talking about before
which is on one level I mean both of us
I think we watch this sort of thing
happen and we've got this kind of deep
visceral sense of we're losing these
really powerful institutions or these in
to shion's are kind of dissolving in
front of our faces but at the same time
we've both been able to make the leap
into the independent media like in some
ways this is a kind of really weird
business opportunity to and to be able
to kind of speak freely because we're
outside the institutions and it feels
like a really like how do you deal with
that because I guess you're watching all
of this stuff any energized by it but
also feeling wow I've got something new
to talk about on the podcast and people
are going to love it so how do you
balance those two things yeah it's
complicated I mean I I'm really
fortunate and I still have a foot in
mainstream media and that you know I
have a book coming out I was lucky to
like be able to sign on with a big
publisher it'll be out in April the
quickfix please buy it quick fix is the
name I'm torn on this in a lot of ways I
think Katy and I would both rather have
it be the case that journalism is
healthy and thriving and people aren't
I've throw money at two assholes on a
podcast talking about internet nonsense
but because mainstream media is
increasingly unable to have normal
conversations being had by people all
over the country will jump in will seize
that opportunity and we've been so
gratified at the success so far and
genuinely shocked at how quickly this
has become this now supports us more
than supports us people should maybe
take some lessons from that maybe the
the outlets like The Times and other
main mainstream outlets that would never
ever hosts a podcast like this should
should perhaps consider the money and
the viewers they're leaving on the table
most likely outcome is that journalism's
are going to continue to collapse and
the next round of funding or whatever
will I think be toward efforts more like
ours I would rather a thousand
ProPublica sprout I'd rather have there
be investigative journal I mean if
there's like a if the Columbus Ohio
Police Department hasn't made your
scandal who the hell is gonna cover that
that's much more important than what
Katie and I do and and that's what I'm
worried about is that you know let's say
a year from now there's ten blocked and
reported twenty more people can make a
living doing that kind of commentary and
and making fun of the demise of
progressive journalism well being
progressive themselves
I just that's not as important as actual
journalism in reporting so in that
sounds like it whatever qualms I have
with The Times they still do really good
investigative stuff they still have some
of the most talented reporters in the
country same with the Washington Post
same with other outlets where
increasingly can't read their culture
coverage because it's just I can't I
read the Wesleyan student paper if I
want those takes so I don't want these
outlets to collapse I want in a sense I
want them to thrive I mean just fun
journalism it's a weird situation
and I don't want my entire life to be
covering and talking about this stuff
because it's exhausting and yeah I'm
lucky the book I have coming out is not
about the stuff it's about weightier
issues so it's such a weird time and two
months ago I was just disconsolate about
the state of journalism I still AM but
now I feel like I have a life raft and I
feel there's a little bit of survivor's
guilt that other people don't have that
life raft thanks for watching and see
you soon
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
you